Guide to the William Somerset Maugham collection, 1921-1979 (inclusive), 1921-1958 (bulk) M0013
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
William Somerset Maugham collection,
Bulk, 1921-1958
1921-1979
M0013
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
2.5 Linear feet (600 items).
Alanson, Bertram E., 1877-1958
Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965
General note
All letters are from W. Somerset Maugham to Bertram Alanson in San Francisco unless otherwise noted.
General note
Boxes 1,2,2b 3: copy of The Trembling of a Leaf
Biographical Note
Bertram E. Alanson was born January 8, 1877 in San Francisco, California. He was an investment broker and served as President of the San Francisco Stock Exchange. Alanson was a personal friend of Maugham as well as his stockbroker. He collected first editions of Maugham's work and other materials about Maugham. Alanson died May 25, 1958.
William Somerset Maugham was born in Paris, France January 25, 1874. He studied medicine, but gave it up for literature. He wrote short stories, essays, and novels. He died in Nice, France December 15, 1965.
Scope Note
This collection consists mainly of W. Somerset Maugham's correspondence with Bertram Alanson, dating from 1921 through 1958 when Alanson died. Alanson was Maugham's investment consultant, but more importantly he was Maugham's friend. The letters are very revealing about Maugham's activities, his philosophy, his works.
There is additional correspondence to Alanson; some concerning Maugham and some are written by members of Maugham's family.
Provenance:
Gift of Bertram E. Alanson, 1957 and 1958.
Access Restrictions:
None.
- 1921-1924, 21 letters (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1. S. S. Wolverine State, Pacific Mail S.S.G.”, [1921] February 26 “; ANS 1p. + envelope
    Scope and Contents note
    Thank you for stay in San Francisco.
  - 2. Singapore, 1921 April 25; TLS 2pp.
    Excursions in the jungle, infant daughter.
  - 3. Hotel Sanatorium Tosari [India], 1921 August 23; TLS 2pp.
    San Francisco, German films, WSM had been hoping to write pictures, Malay cruise.
  - 4. Garoet, 1921 November 18; ALS 2pp. (2)
    Dedication of The Trembling of a Leaf.
  - 5. [London], [1922] January 28; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Legal problems.
  - 6. [London], [1922] July 25; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Going to N. Y. for play of “East of Suez”.
  - 7. Upper Burma, 1922 October 25; TLS 1p.
    Pony trip from Mandalay to Bangkok, story in Christmas Good Housekeeping.
  - 8. Shanghai, 1923 March 8; TNS 1p.
    Will be sailing to Vancouver, B.C., wants reservations at St. Francis in San Francisco.
  - 9. Hollywood, 1923 April 30; TLS ANS
    San Francisco, rodeo.
  - 10. New York, [1923] May 8; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    A “thank you” for kidness, etc. in San Francisco.
  - 11. RMS “Aquitania”, [1923] May 25; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Investment, agency fee on “Rain”, Haxton to have made it into play, drinking.
  - 12. Rangoon, Burma, [1923] August 17; ALS 2pp.
    To produce play at once.
  - 13. [London], [1923] August 24; TLS 2pp. + envelope
    Rehearsing, Gerald.
  - 14. New York, 1923 October 6; TLS 2pp. + envelope
    English production of “The Camel's Back”, Charles Chaplin, success of play “Rain”.
  - 15. New York Te, 1923 October 15
    Thanks for present, “opening postponed”.
  - 16. New York, 1923 October 25; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Flask, rehearsals of [The Camel's Back], other plays.
  - 17. Washington, D.C. Gerald Haxton to BA, 1923 November 7; TL 2pp. + envelope
    Thanks for sympathy, opening of “Camel's Back”.
  - 18. [London], [1924] January 14; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Producers, plays, etc., trip to Central America, horse, London.
  - 19. London, [1924] January 30; TNS 1p. + envelope
    Thanks, to go to Paris, working on a novel.
  - 20. [London], 1924 June 19; ALS 2pp.
    Alanson's marriage, finished novel, to New York in autumn, translations of work.
  - 21. New York, 1924 October 1; TLS 2pp.
    Planning Central American trip, wedding present, hotel prices.
- 1925-1937, 28 letters (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1. New York Tel., 1925 March 13
    Rehearsals of “Rain”, sailing on “Aquitania”.
  - 2. [Paris], 1925 May 17; TLS with ms. corrections. 2pp.
    Rehearsals of “Rain”, Tallulah Bankhead, production, Margaret Bannerman, “The Letter”, legal problems, “The Painted Veil”, wife building house, Natoma.
  - 3. [Brides-Les-Baines], 1925 July 9; TLS 4pp. with half page ANS
    Taking a cure, “Natoma”, finances, Circles Dramatics, Inc. “The Letter”, sending withdrawn edition of “Painted Veil”, daily routine, catastrophe at Santa Barbara, Mr. Latham.
  - 4. London, [1926] May 20; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Death, houses, arrangement with his wife.
  - 5. New York, [1927] March 15; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Collected a trunk of stories in the East, Saigon to Marseilles, personal, Latham.
  - 6. Cap Ferrat, [1927] August 1; TLS 1p. + envelope
    House, invitation, workmen.
  - 7. New York, [1927 October 11]; TLS 1p.
    Rehearsals, interviews, plays “The Letter” and “The Constant Wife”, villa.
  - 8. Cap Ferrat, 1928 February 4; TLS 1p. + envelope
    House finances, book on his travels in the Far East.
  - 9. Cap Ferrat, [1930] June 15; ALS 2pp.
    Alanson, Pres. of S. F. Stock Exchange, Palm Beach, Honolulu memories, The Gentleman in the Parlour, “ Notomas”, finances.
  - 10. Cap Ferrat, [1930] July 15; TLS 1p.
    Book, “Natomas”, financial questions.
  - 11. London, [1930] October 31
    New car, successful play [“The Breadwinner?”], America too unsettled for him.
  - 12. Cap Ferrat, [1931] April 24; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Financial situation, wants to go to Constantinople.
  - 13. Cap Ferrat, [1932] January 27; TLS 1p. + envelope
    Finances, Riviera.
  - 14. London, [1932] November 18; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Sending new novel, Mrs. G. B. Storm, an author, Prohibition.
  - 15. Cap Ferrat, [1933] January 22; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Prohibition, book on Spain.
  - 16. Cap Ferrat, 1933 May 30; TLS 1p. with ANS.
    Peter Stern market.
  - 17. London, [1933] October 24; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Germany.
  - 18. London, [1933] November 13; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    A celebration for Alanson.
  - 19. Cap Ferrat, 1934 January 27; TLS 1p.
    Thanks for “cheeque”, cost of living in France, film arrived.
  - 20. Paris, [1934] April 29; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Returned from six weeks in Spain, machine gun firing in Madrid.
  - 21. Cap Ferrat, [1934] July 16; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    “Natomas Co.”, financial, work.
  - 22. Cap Ferrat, 1934 October 12; TLS 1p.
    Work, finances, trip to U.S.
  - 23. Cap Ferrat, 1935, February 4; TLS 1p. + envelope
    Finances, G. B. Stern.
  - 24. Cap Ferrat, 1935 May 19; TLS 1p. + envelope
    Thank you.
  - 25. London, [1936] November 1; ALS 2pp. + envelope, 50 copies,
    Reprint of an article, daughter's marriage, finances, work, Doubleday anthology of short stories.
  - 26. Paris, [1937] May 16; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Finances, Theatre, wants to found prize.
  - 27. London, [1937] October 13; TLS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, Theatre, nephew.
  - 28. London, [1937] November 12; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, Robin.
- 1938-1940, 19 letters (Box 1, Folder 3)
  General note
  1st letter formerly 13/1/16 item 4
  - 1. Cap Ferrat, 1938 May 13; TLS 1p. with AN + envelope
    Money tied up in Germany.
  - 2. Cap Ferrat, 1938 May 22; TLS 1p. + envelope
    Finances, family.
  - 3. London, [1938] October 23; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, motor accident.
  - 4. New York, [1939] February 25; TLS 4pp. + envelope
    Mail, flue [sic], photos, parties, sailing from N. Y., picket against involvement in Spain, radio program, Gerald, Sunday articles, Halifax's speech.
  - 5. Chicago, [1939 February?]; ALS 3pp.
    Thanks for kindnesses, hospitality, train trip.
  - 6. London, [1939] April 4; ALS 2pp.
    Finances, Robin + political career, in service, [War].
  - 7. Montecatini Termi, Italy, [1939] June 12; ALS 2pp.
    War.
  - 8. Cap Ferrat, 1939 July 20; TLS 1 1/2pp. + envelope
    Finances, family, Robin Christmas Holiday, Hitler and war.
  - 9. Cap Ferrat, [1939] September 25; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Alan's visit to BA, mail, Robin & viscouncy, finances & legal business.
  - 10. Cap Ferrat, [1939] October 24; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Mail, Christmas Holiday, censorship, contraband.
  - 11. Cap Ferrat, [1939] November 18; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    [a trust?] for Robin, a week with French army at front, armaments plant, Alsace, driving military car, arms build up.
  - 12. Cap Ferrat, 1940 May 15; TLS 1p.
    Letter inserted formerly 13/1/16 Item 6
    Business, new job with government, war.
  - 13. Cap Ferrat, [1940?] May 20; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Letter inserted formerly 13/1/16 item 23
    Letter about Alanson, finances, `29 crash.
  - 14. Oyster Bay, New York, [1940] October 13; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, Lisbon trip, taxes, mail, refugee children, air raids.
  - 15. New York, [1940] October 26; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Moved to N. Y., travel.
  - 16. New York, [1940] November 8; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Planning trip to U.S., N.Y. activities.
  - 17. New York, [1940] December 17; ALS 3pp. + envelope
    Trip to S.F., Seattle & Pullman.
- 1941-42, 17 letters (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1. Chicago, [1941] March 17; ALS 3 1/2pp. + envelope
    Speaking engagements, to write a film for Selznick.
  - 2. New York, 1941 April 2; TLS 1p. + envelope
    Finances, flu.
  - 3. New York, [1941] April 30; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, no news from Hollywood, Dr. Benjamin.
  - 4. Los Angeles, 1941 June 5; TLS 1p. with AN + envelope
    Home in L.A., grandchildren, wine.
  - 5. Los Angeles, 1941 June 9; TLS 1p. with ms. note
    Alanson's visit.
  - 6. Los Angeles, [1941 August 8]; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Lisa leaving, to visit S.F., book, Paramount buying movie rights, earnings, wine.
  - 7. Los Angeles, [1941] August 13; ALS 1p. + envelope
    A professor doing a bibliography of his works.
  - 8. New York, [1941] November 19; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Wine, So. Carolina, Alan.
  - 9. So. Carolina, [1941] December 12; ALS 1 3/4pp. + envelope
    Gerald, Robin.
  - 10. Parker's Ferry, [1942] February 3; ALS 1 1/2pp.
    Finances, Br. Treasury, marlaria, “negro” servants.
  - 11. So. Carolina, [1942] February 22; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    To go to New York, finances.
  - 12. S. Carolina, Parker's Ferry., [1942] March 24; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Doing propaganda work, Robin has had tanks shot out from under him.
  - 13. Edgartown, Massachusetts, [1942] July 16; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Robin wounded, finances, “The Razor's Edge” doing well.
  - 14. Edgartown, Mass., [1942] July 27; ALS 1 1/4pp. + envelope
  - 15. Edgartown, Mass., [1942] August 19; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, Anthology nearly finished, Doubleday Editor coming.
  - 16. Edgartown, Mass., [1942] August 22; ALS 1p.
    Personal, death, Gerald.
  - 17. [Parker's Ferry], [1942] November 25; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Went to Boston, New Haven, etc., cottage and grounds, maids, chickens, life style.
- 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1. [Parkers] S.C., [1943] January 13; ALS 1 1/2pp. + envelope
    Business, Gerald, [G] has left WSM's employment, weather, rehearsals postponed.
  - 2. Parker's Ferry, 1943 March 31; TLS 2pp. + envelope
    Writing 1500 words a day by hand, Karl Pfeiffer compiling Maugham bibliography, garden.
  - 3. Parker's Ferry, [1943] April 29; TLS 2pp.
    Cancer tests negative, “Sheppey” not a success, movie deal, Gerald very ill.
  - 4. New York, [1943] May 30; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Travel, Alain Searle, trip to India, Gerald, inflation.
  - 5. Edgartown, [1943] August 18; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finished novel, travel, Robin.
  - 6. Edgartown, [1943] September 7; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Investments, trip to Reno.
  - 7. New York, [1943] October 29; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Gerald, rehearsals of “Sheppey”. novel being serialized in Red Book.
  - 8. New York, [1943] November 12; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Finances, Gerald, rehearsals of play.
  - 9. London, [1943] December 6; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, Doubledays.
  - 10. Parkers Ferry, [1944] January 23; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Gerald, donations, education.
  - 11. Parker's, [1944] January 31; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Alansons to visit, New Orleans, “Liza children's guardian”.
  - 12. New York, [1944] May 16; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Gerald's illness, financial business, “Sheppey” a failure but book a success, movie contract.
  - 13. Parker's Ferry, [1944] July 1; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Gerald, movie contract for “Razor's Edge”, finances, to establish author's prize.
  - 14. Saranac Lake, NY to Lake Tahoe, California, [1944] August 1; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, Gerald, John Hopkins.
  - 15. Edgartown, [1944] August 14; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, [vacation], Gerald.
  - 16. Parker's Ferry, [1944] August 26; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Death of BA's brother, success of “Razor's Edge”.
  - 17. Parker's Ferry, [1944] November 24; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Business, finances.
  - 18. Cap Ferrat, [1944] December 22; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Finances, Alan.
- 1945-1946, 16 letters (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1. Hollywood, [1945] June 7; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Financial business, Alan, George Cukor.
  - 2. New York, 1945 September 26; TLS 1p. + envelope
    Suite at Plaza, Kaiser & Co., domestic difficulties.
  - 3. [New York], [cvr. 1945] October 16; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Financial business.
  - 4. New York, [1945] October 31; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Oil magnate.
  - 5. Parkers, [1946] January 22; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Thanks, Alan, financial business, working on novel.
  - 6. Parker's, 1946 February 16; TLS 1p.
    Novel, trust fund for children.
  - 7. New York, [1946] May 8; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Interviews, etc., book done, propaganda, “Athes” (ship), Sam Behrman making a play of story “Jane”, revolt at Alcatraz.
  - 8. New York, 1946 May 21; TLS 1p. + envelope
    Denies being anti-Semitic.
  - 9. Cap Ferrat, 1946 June 15; ALS 2pp. with AN + envelope
    Arrival in Marseilles, shell damage to house and property, Germans took all the writing paper.
  - 10. London, 1946 October 2; TLS 1p. + envelope
    Financial business, post-war conditions.
  - 11. London, 1946 November 28; TLS 1 1/2pp.
    France still unsettled, business, Robin, “The Razor's Edge” a success in NY, successful revival of first play “Lady Frederick”.
  - 12. London, 1946 December 6; TLS 1p.
  - 13. London, 1946 December 7; TLS 1p.
    Alansons coming to France.
  - 14. Cap Ferrat, 1946 December 16; TLS 1/2p. + envelope
  - 15. Cap Ferrat, 1946 December 20; TLS 1p.
  - 16. Cap Ferrat, 1946 December 20; TLS 1p. with AN + envelope
    White coats, visit.
- 1947-1949, (26 letters) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1. Cap Ferrat to [London, S.F.], [1947] February 13; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Weather, visit, “Rigoletto”.
  - 2. Cap Ferrat, 1947 March 13; TLS 1p. with AN
    Financial business, Alan, Maugham prize.
  - 3. Cap Ferrat, [1947] September 8; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Trip to Spain postponed, other trips, rice, smuggling, finances, trust for grandchildren, Alan, malaria.
  - 4. New York, [1947] November 11; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Trip from L.A. to Charleston, house, Parker's Ferry.
  - 5. Cap Ferrat to New York, 1948 February 4; TLS 1p.
    Alansons to visit, gas short for individuals, dollars and black market.
  - 6. Cap Ferrat to New York, 1948 February 12; TNS 1p. + envelope
    To meet Alansons' ship at Cannes.
  - 7. Cap Ferrat to New York, 1948 February 17; TNS 1p. + envelope
    Business.
  - 8. Cap Ferrat to Paris, [1948] April 7; ANS 2pp. + envelope
    Visit, thanks.
  - 9. Madrid to New York, [1948] April 26; ALS 3 1/4pp. + envelope
    Interviews, spoke in Spanish on the radio.
  - 10. Seville, [1948] May 13; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Spain, people, Prado, Goya, Duquesa de Luccas “a jolly old girl”, Alvarez in Madrid, Alan.
  - 11. Cap Ferrat, [1948] June 18; ALS 2pp.
    Marked “personal” Moccasins, people's welcome to WSM on trip.
  - 12. London, [1948 November 9]; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    “Lord Mayor's Day”, sailing for N. Y.
  - 13. New York, [1948] December 24; ALS 2 1/2pp.
    Finances, trip from America, Christmas at Oyster Bay.
  - 14. [Cap Ferrat (letter), [1947 or 48] December 24; ALS 2pp. + envelope New York (envelope)]
    Birthday, finances, grandchildren, Alan, travel restrictions.
  - 15. France, ND; Fragment of a cover
  - 16. Cap Ferrat, 1948 February 8; Envelope only
  - 17. Rome, [1949] January 12; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Taxes, Mabel's birthday.
  - 18. New York, [1949] February 9; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Food, finances, “bankers lunch”, Overseas Press Club, Allen, Alais.
  - 19. Cap Ferrat, [1949] March 17; ALS 2pp.
  - 20. Cap Ferrat, 1949 March 17; TLS 1/2p.
    Business letter, inheritence tax, concern over deed signed in San Francisco and financial management of his estate upon his death.
  - 21. Cap Ferrat, [1949] April 10; ALS 2pp.
    An article, Norman Crump, Liza, finances, has purchased paintings by Pizzaro, Renault, Renoir, and Monet; black market; French Consul.
  - 22. Cap Ferrat, [1949] April 30; ALS 2 1/2pp.
    An article by Norman Crump, Liza, finances, purchase of Impressionist pictures by Pizzaro, Renoir and Monet.
  - 23. [Abano] Italy, [1949] May 8; ALS 2pp.
    Italy, Alan, health.
  - 24. Abano, [1949] May 18; ALS 2pp.
    Riviera, [Albano?] a strange place, baths treatment, publication date set for October 15.
  - 25. Cap Ferrat, [1949] May 21; ALS 1p.
    Mabel Alanson's illness.
  - 26. Cap Ferrat, [1949] August 28; ALS 2pp.
    Guests, essay, the Behrmans who own The Book of the Month Club; trip to Spain and Portugal, Jerry Zipkin.
  - 27. NP, [1949] ND; envelope
  - 28. London, England (The Dorchester), 1949 November 13; TLS 2pp.
    Taxes, finances, Trust, will.
  - 29. London, England (The Dorchester), [1949] December 3; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Alan.
- 1950-1951, 19 letters (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1. Cap Ferrat, [1950] January 13; ALS 2pp.
    Finances, yearly grant to young authors, British political scene, bought a female nude by Renoir.
  - 2. Cap Ferrat, [1950] February 16; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Solicitor, death, garden, Alan.
  - 3. Porte de G Kasbah Eilala, [1950] April 13; ALS (picture postcard)
    Morocco Morocco, palace.
  - 4. [Morocco [Atlas Mountains?]], [1950 May 1]; ALS (picture postcard)
    Morocco, Taroudant, city gates, hot weather.
  - 5. Cap Ferrat, [1950] May 14; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Cities in Tunisia, Egypt and Turkey, Laza's child, Paul Mellen and Anthony Eden are godfathers.
  - 6. Cap Ferrat, [1950] June [24]; ALS 2pp.
    Columbia Records, Dr. Wolf.
  - 7. Cap Ferrat, [1950] July [24]; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Pen, RKO, Library of Congress party.
  - 8. Cap Ferrat, 1950 August 14; TLS 1p. + AN [1/2p. at bottom]
    “Churchill Magazine”, Cakes, AND Ale.
  - 9. France (Carlton Majestic), [1950] September 5; ALS 1p.
    Finances, Showing of “Trio”.
  - 10. New York to New York, [1950 September 28]; Typed inviation, no signature. 1p. + envelope
  - 11. New York, [1950] October 19; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Bought “the Renoir”, television show, Morgan Library.
  - 12. London, 1950 October 25; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Thanks for sympathy.
  - 13. Cap Ferrat, [1950] December 22; ALS 2pp.
    Writing, Frieda seriously ill, Christmas presents, Lady Bateman, customs.
  - 14. Cap Ferrat, [1950] December 25; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Christmas party, finances.
  - 15. Cap Ferrat, [1951] January 14; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances, death of Frieda von [Leidlitz], an essay published, [70th] birthday.
  - 16. Cap Ferrat, [1951] March 12; ALS 1p. + envelope
  - 17. Cap Ferrat, [1951] March 31; ALS 1 1/2pp. + envelope
    Birthday, finances, TV introductions.
  - 18. Venice, Italy, [1951] May 11; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Venice, weather, Academy speech.
  - 19. Cap Ferrat, [1951] July 12; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Academy speech, introduction to Kepling's stories, to go up the Nile.
  - 1952, 18 letters (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1. Cap Ferrat, [1952] January 6; ALS 1 1/2pp. + envelope
    Birthday wishes to Mabel, festive Christmas & New Year, stories a success.
  - 2. Cap Ferrat, [1952] January 26; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Fan mail, gifts.
  - 3. Cap Ferrat, [1952] January 29; ALS 2pp. + envelope
  - 4. Cap Ferrat, [1952] March 2; ALS 1 1/2pp. + envelope
    Finances, court case, rheumatism.
  - 5. Cap Ferrat, [1952] March 24; ALS 1 1/2pp. + envelope (note address on bottom of 2nd page--not WSM's writing)
    Finances.
  - 6. Vaud, Switzerland, [1952] April 29; ALS 1 3/4pp + envelope
    Stay in mountains for health.
  - 7. Netherlands, [1952] May 29; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Alanson's health and his own.
  - 8. Cap Ferrat, [1952] June 30; ALS 1pp. + envelope
    Letter inserted formerly 13/1/16 item 11
    Alanson recovering.
  - 9. Cap Ferrat, [1952] August 27; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Sent color copy of his portrait by Graham Sutherland.
  - 10. Cap Ferrat, [1952] August 26; ALS 4pp.
    Bath cures, Austria.
  - 11. Switzerland (Ouchy-Lausanne), [1952] September 27; ALS 4pp. + envelope
    Health.
  - 12. Switzerland (Ouchy-Lausanne), [1952] October 5; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Finances
  - 13. Switzerland (Ouchy-Lausanne), [1952] ND; envelope
  - 14. London (The Dorchester), [1952] October 13; ALS 2pp.
    Finances, work tours.
  - 15. London (The Dorchester), [1952] November 26; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Photo of Alansons
  - 16. London (The Dorchester), [1952] December 5; ALS (short one page note)
  - 17. London (The Dorchester), [1952] December 16; ALS 4pp. + envelope
- 1953, 22 letters (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1. Cap Ferrat, [1953] January 20; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Clinic in Switzerland, tax problems, McCabe, financial business, approaching 80th year.
  - 2. Cap Ferrat, [1953] February 17; ALS 1p. + envelope
  - 3. Cap Ferrat, [1953] February 26; ALS 1 1/4pp. + envelope
    Brother's visit, party.
  - 4. Cap Ferrat, [1953] March 2; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Taxes, finances, George Cukor.
  - 5. Cap Ferrat, [1953] March 14; ALS 2pp. + envelope
  - 6. Cap Ferrat, [1953] March 20; ALS 2pp. + envelope
  - 7. Cap Ferrat, [1953] March 27; ALS 2pp. + envelope
  - 8. Cap Ferrat, [1953 March 31]; ALS 1 1/4pp. + envelope (letter difficult to read)
    Business, Robin.
  - 9. Cap Ferrat, [1953] April 13; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Business, guests.
  - 10. Istanbul, [1953 April 26]; Postcard written and initialled 1 p.
    Sightseeing.
  - 11. Rhodes, [1953 May 29]; Postcard ANS
    Island and travel.
  - 12. Cap Ferrat, [1953] June 21; ALS 3pp. + envelope
    Travels.
  - 13. Cap Ferrat, [1953] July 18; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Politics, prices.
  - 14. Cap Ferrat, [1953] July 23; ALS 3pp. + envelope
    England, ceremony at palace.
  - 15. [Germany] Travel., [1953 August 1]; postcard ANS
  - 16. Cap Ferrat, [1953] September 1]; ALS 1p. + envelope
    TV rights.
  - 17. Cap Ferrat, [1953] September 14; ALS 1 1/8pp. + envelope
  - 18. London (The Dorchester), [1953] October 30; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Charlie Chaplin.
  - 19. N.Y. (Plaza), [1953] November 7; ALS 2pp.
    Lecture at Columbia, played bridge with General Eisenhower, Doug Black, speeches, Columbia records.
  - 20. London (The Dorchester), [1953] November 12; ALS 2pp. + envelope
  - 21. London (The Dorchester), [1953] December 23?; ALS 1p. + envelope
    Gale blowing.
  - 22. Cap Ferrat, [1953?] December 26?; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    New Years note, audience with Queen Elizabeth.
- 1954, 14 letters (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1. Paris (Hotel Vendome), [1954] January 9; ALS 2pp.
    [WSM] ill, 80th birthday (in London) approaching, finances.
  - 2. Paris (Vendome), [1954] January 12; ANS 1p. + envelope (addition to January 9 letter)
    Finances, attorney (& suit) in N.Y.
  - 3. Cap Ferrat, [1954] February 5; ALS 2pp. + envelope
    Thanks, 80th birthday, health, lawsuit in N.Y.
  - 4. Cap Ferrat, [1954] April 5; ALS 1 1/2pp. + envelope